# Aki Fukai Product Designer Curriculum Vitae

Last updated: Jan 2023

#### In a nutshell

As a **senior/lead product designer** with more than 20 years and more than 10 years of product & service building experience. I do my best work within small and de-siloed **product teams**. I help amplifying the **strategic impact of design** and shaping the way of working. Together we work on large, **complex projects** over multiple iterations – and form a **trusted and sustainable relationship**.

I'm a Swiss citizen currently live with my family in **Hamburg Germany** working mostly remotely.

#### Contact

**Cell DE:** +49 172 431 15 00

Email: aki@fukai.ch Web: www.fukai.ch Nationality: Swiss

Current residence: Hamburg, Germany

Twitter: @FUKAldesign Profile on: LinkedIn Profile on: Xing Page Index

Contact Details & Current Situation p. 1
About Me & Digital Products p. 2
Selected Clients & Agencies p. 3
Work Experience & Education p. 4
Project Highlights p. 4-5

#### **About Me**

With my work I strive to **improve people's lives** by solving complex problems with simple and useful solutions. By shaping technology into thoughtful digital products that matter I work towards the answers — for the people who use it and the people who provide and grow it — with engineers, product/business people, domain experts and real users.

My tools are user research, UX consulting, interaction design and user interface design. I have been developing concepts, strategies and designs focused on web based products and services including mobile since 1998.

I believe the best results emerge from a **close collaboration**, be it in internal interdisciplinary teams, or through a consultancy in a **committed relationship** with clients.

In my spare time I am with **my family**, travel and learn from different cultures and practice Chen Style Taiji. I love clean and useful (Swiss) typography, **minimal** and **'super normal' design** and **learning new things** in live and in my profession.

I am a **native German speaker** of Swiss and Japanese heritage. I am **fluent in English** and have an advanced basic knowledge of **French**.

Selected Clients in alphabetical order

**academics.de** (Die Zeit, Forschung & Lehre)

**Audi** 

Beiersdorf (Eucerin)

Baden-Württemberg Ministry of State

Bentley

BMW (bmw.com)

Chrysler (Jeep, Chrysler)

collectAl (Liquid Labs / Otto Group)

**CTS Eventim AG** 

Daimler / Mercedes-Benz

Deutsche Bahn AG

dtp entertainment AG

enfore AG

Henkel

**JPC** 

Klinikum Südstadt Rostock

KRAFT Foods (Milka, Kraft)

LG Electronics

natcon7 (part of Nordex)

**Netbreeze** (now part of Microsoft)

Otto Reisen, Reiseland

**PlasticPlan** (MVPF)

receeve GmbH

Rossmann

SAP SE

**SBB Informatik AG** 

Scout24 Schweiz AG

Siemens Medical Solutions

Sony Deutschland

Sqoops, Doomster (doomster.de) until 11.2008

**STURM und DRANG** (partner of MetaDesign)

Tagesspiegel Media

Telefónica Germany (o2)

Tipp-Kick

Trilux

**Unify (formerly Siemens Enterprise Communications)** 

University of Applied Sciences, Dept of Design HAW, Hamburg

Various medium-sized companies and multinational groups of different branches and municipal institutions

#### Selected Agencies in alphabetical order

brink & martens GmbH

**D-LABS GmbH** 

DDD Design GmbH

**EYELABEL Digital Communication** 

#### **Experience One AG**

Freiland Netzlösungen GmbH

#### frog design

Häberlein & Mauerer AG

IconMedialab AG

Interone GmbH

Jung von Matt/next

Kabel New Media AG

#### Neue Digitale Razorfish GmbH

Nolte & Lauth GmbH

OgilyvInteractive

Philipp und Keuntje

Plan.Net

#### STURM und DRANG, Innovation Insights

superReal GmbH (part of DEPT®)

TEMPODOME GmbH

**WowBiz GmbH** 

## **Work Experience**

#### 2004 - today

Freelance senior/lead product designer (UX/UI), concept developer/consultant IA/UX

**Startups:** i.a. PlasticPlan, enfore AG, Liquid Labs **Companies:** i.a. SBB, SAP, Daimler, Telefónica, SMB

& DACH and global brands

#### 07.2022 - today

Freelance lead/senior UX/UI designer Clients: Babymarkt, Tagesspiegel, Mercedes-Benz.io

#### 02.2022 - 07.2022

Freelance lead product designer Client: PlasticPlan

#### 06.2020 - today

Partner & senior product designer App: Hello Meet

#### 06.2018 - 05.2020

(Freelance) sr. product designer Client: enfore AG

#### 02.2016 - 02.2018

(Freelance) senior interaction designer

Client: collectAl (at Liquid Labs/Otto Group)

**11.2015 - 09.2016** (40-60%)

Freelance sr. interaction designer Client: SBB

#### 07.2015 - 10.2015

Freelance sr. interaction designer (design system)

Client: SAP SE

#### 02.2015 - 04.2015

Senior user experience designer

Client: Scout24 Schweiz AG

#### 12.2013 - 10.2014

Freelance senior interaction designer

Client: natcon7 GmbH

#### 09.2013 - 01.2014

Freelance senior interaction designer

**Agency:** frog design **Client:** Unify (Siemens)

#### 01.2013 - 04.2013

Freelance UX designer Client: Immonet

#### 05.2011 - 09.2011

Freelance sr. art director / design lead

Agency: Razorfish Client: Telefónica (o2)

#### 2008 - 2013 (intermittent)

Freelance art director, IxD, UX consultant

Agency: WowBiz GmbH Clients i.a.: Aquila Capital,

Rossmann, Netbreeze

#### 2006 - 2008

Freelance art-/creative director, designer **Agency:** DDD Design GmbH **Clients i.a.:** Audi,

DaimlerChrysler (Mercedes-Benz, Jeep, Chrysler,

Dodge), jpc.de, lesen.de 2003 - 2004 Art director **Agency:** Spirit Link GmbH

**Clients:** SiemensMedical Solutions, Siemens, the agency's relaunch (website and PM software)

#### 2001 - 2002

Art director and designer

**Agency:** GiveMe5 Online-Kommunikation GmbH **Clients i.a.:** Bentley, Curtius Lütten von Perfall Werbeagentur GmbH, Otto Reisen, Reiseland

#### 2000 - 2001

Screen designer, UI designer Agency: IconMedialab AG

**Clients i.a.:** FMCG, intranet applications, various usability focused projects and web specials

#### 2000 - 2000

Freelance screen designer

Agency: Ahead Deutschland, now Valtech

Clients i.a.: FMCG, i.a. Milka

#### 1998 - 2000

Freelance screen designer **Agency:** Kabel New Media AG

Client: BMW.com

#### 1997 - 1997

Screen designer (internship) **Agency:** Fork Unstable Media

Clients i.a.: lifestyle magazine 'blond', Spar

### **Education**

#### 1994 - 1998

HAW Hamburg, Fakultät Design, Medien und Information / Department Design:

Kommunikationsdesign / communication design

## **Project Highlights**

For a more visual look at projects until the end of 2021 take a look at my PDF portfolio.

# Making plastic packaging sustainable, with data – Plastic Plan

**Duration:** 02.2022 - 07.2022

**Done:** Designing the human centred interface on top of an Al-supported data service empowering enterprises to manage complex packaging data transparently & enabling teams across units to

make product packaging sustainable, **Technology:** Web, Vue.js, Tailwind **Role:** Lead product designer

## Group scheduling made simple – Hello Meet

**Duration:** 01.2018 - today

**Done:** Hypothesis driven product design and development, JTBD based user flows and UIs, new features, continuous improvement, co-shaping

and testing the business model **Technology:** iOS, Android, Web, React **Role:** Partner & senior product designer

## Helping local stores to run their businesses – enfore AG

**Duration:** 06.2018 - 05.2020

**Done:** Reservations, pick-up & delivery and dashboard widgets in enforePOS, online presence,

email & business documents

**Technology:** Web/mail (responsive), enforeDasher,

enforeDonner

Role: Senior product designer

# End-to-end digital collections, redefined – collectAl

**Duration:** 02.2016 - 02.2018

**Done:** White label digital self-service dunning, collections & payment processes, merchant portal **Technology:** Web/mail (respons.), iOS, iPad, React

Role: Senior product designer

# iPad and web/desktop app for SBB based on GIS technology

**Duration:** 11.2015 - 09.2016

**Done:** UX concept, flows, mockups, prototypes

(Sketch/InVision)

Technology: Web (responsive), iOS, iPad

Role: Senior interaction designer

### Fiori App Finder for SAP Global Design

**Duration:** 07.2015 - 10.2015

**Done:** UX concepts, flows, Prototypes (Axure RP Pro), Fiori UX design guidelines for App Finder &

Fiori Launchpad

Technology: Web (responsive), iOS, iPhone

**Role:** Senior interaction designer **Direct client** (with D-Labs)

# **Unify Project Ansible – platform for unified enterprise communication**

**Duration:** 09.2013 - 02.2014

**Done:** Conceived and documented the interaction design throughout (web and mobile) for various features e.g. conferencing, voice/video calls in collaboration with the client – from overarching

concepts to detailed UI states

Technology: Web (responsive), iOS, iPhone

Role: Senior interaction designer

With: frog design

### Social Media Summary for Netbreeze –

a Swiss ETH spin-off, acquired by Microsoft 2013

**Duration:** 01.2012 - 06.2012

**Done:** Concept incl. visualisation of a timeline-based application UI, widgets & report/data viz – for the Swiss social media monitoring startup **Role:** Concept developer (IA/UX), UX designer, art

director & UI designer

With: WowBiz

# Comprehensive telco portal and e-commerce relaunch of o2.de

(Telefónica Germany)

**Duration:** 05.2011 - 10.2011

**Done:** Simplification of the shopping flow, Optimisation of the checkout process UX, Unified teaser concept, Tablet/touch enabled, Client side UX consultation, Brand alignment,

Style guide

Role: Senior art director and design lead

With: Neue Digitale / Razorfish